you
Krishnamurti in dialogue with Dr. Alan
W. Anderson. J. Krishnamurti was born in
South India and educated in England. For
the past 40 years he has been speaking
in the United States, Europe, India,
Australia, and other parts of the world.
From the outset of his life's
work he repudiated all connections with organized
religions and ideologies and said that
his only concern was to set men
absolutely unconditionally free. He is the
author of many books, among them the
Awakening of Intelligence, the Urgency of
Change, Freedom from the Known, and the
Flight of the Eagle. This is one
of a series of dialogues between Krishnamurti
and Dr. Alan W. Anderson, who
is professor of religious studies at San
Diego State University where he teaches
Indian and Chinese scriptures and the
oracular tradition. Dr. Anderson, a
published poet, received his degree from
Columbia University and the Union
Theological Seminary. He has been honored
with a Distinguished Teaching Award
from the California State Universities.
Mr. Krishnamurti, we were talking last
time together about death in the context
of living and love, and as I remember just
as we came to the close of what we
were discussing, we thought it would be
good to pursue this in terms of a
further inquiry into education, what
really goes on between teacher and
student when they begin looking together
and what are the traps that
immediately appear and shock. You
mentioned the terror of death, not
simply externally, but internally in relation
to thought, and it seemed to me
perhaps it would be a splendid thing
if we just continued that and went deeper
into it.
So I would like to ask why we
are educated at all. What is the meaning of
this education that people receive?
Apparently they don't understand a
thing of life, they don't understand
fear, pleasure, the whole thing that we
have discussed, and the ultimate fear of death
and the terror of not being. Is it
fear of death and the terror of not
being? Is it that we have become so utterly
materialistic that we are only concerned
with good jobs, money, pleasure, and
superficial amusements, entertainments, whether they
be religious or football, is
it that our whole nature
and structure has become so utterly
meaningless? And when we are educated
to that and to suddenly face something
real, it is terrifying. And as we were saying yesterday,
we are not educated to look at
ourselves, we are not educated to understand the
whole business of living, we are not
educated to look and see what happens if
we face death. So I was wondering,
as we came along this morning, religion, which
we are going to discuss anyhow, has become
merely not only a divisive process but also
utterly meaningless. Maybe two thousand years
as Christianity or three, five as
Hinduism, Buddhism and so on, it has lost
its substance. And we never enquire into what
is religion, what is education, what is living, what
is dying, you know, the whole business of it.
We never ask what is it all about. And when
we do ask, we say, well, life has very little meaning,
and it has very little meaning as we live,
and so we escape into all kinds of fantastic romantic
nonsense which has no reason, which is not
a... we can't discuss or logically enquire, but it's
mere escape from this utter emptiness, a life that one
leads. I don't know if you saw the other day
a group of people adoring a human
being and they are doing most fantastic things,
and that's what they call religion, that's what they
call God. They seem to have lost all reason.
Reason apparently has no meaning anymore either.
A. I did see a documentary that was actually
put on by this station in which the whole meeting
operation was being portrayed between the public
and this individual in this young 15-year-old guru,
Maharaj Ji. And it was... K. Disgusting. A.
Extraordinarily amazing. And it was in many respects revolting.
K. And that's what they call religion. So
shall we begin with religion and go on?
A. Yes, I think it would be a
splendid thing to do. K. All right, sir.
You know, I feel man has always wanted or
tried to find out something beyond the everyday living,
everyday routine, everyday pleasures, everyday activity
of thought. He wanted something much more.
I don't know if you have been to India,
I do not know if you have been to villages.
They put a little stone under a tree, put
some marking on it, next day they have flowers,
and the fourth day people are there, it
has become divinity, it has become something religious.
That same principle is continued in the cathedrals.
It is exactly the same thing when you... mass
and all the rituals in India and all
that. It begins there, the desire for human beings
to find something more than what thought has put together.
Not being able to find it,
they romanticise it, they create symbols,
or somebody who has got a
little bit of this, they worship.
And around that they do all kinds of rituals.
Indian puja, you know, all that
business goes on. And that's called religion,
which has absolutely nothing to do
with behaviour, with our daily life.
So, seeing all this, both
in the West and the East,
in the world of Islam, in the world of Hindu
Buddhism and all that, it is the same principle going on.
Worshipping an image which they have created,
whether it is the Buddha or Jesus or Christ,
it is the human mind that has created the image.
And they worship the image which is their
own. In other words, they are worshipping themselves.
A. And the division, the split grows wider.
K. So religion, when one asks, what is religion,
it is the image of the human being.
So religion, when one asks, what is religion,
obviously one must negate, in the sense,
not brutally cut off, understand all this.
And so negate all the religions.
Negate the religion of India
and the multiple gods and goddesses,
and here the religion of Christianity, which
is an image which they have created,
which is idolatry. They might not like
to call it idolatry, but it is.
It is an idolatry of the mind.
The mind has created the ideal,
and the mind through the hand created
the statue, the glass and so on.
So if one really puts all that aside,
the belief, the belief that the idolatry is the idolatry,
the belief, the superstition, the worship of the person,
worship of an idea, and the
rituals and the tradition, all that,
if one can do it. And
one must do it to find out.
A. Exactly. There is a point of terror here
that is many, many faceted, it seems to me.
It has so many, many different mirrors
that it holds up to one's own dysfunction.
To reach the place where one is
willing to begin, at the point where
he makes this negation in order to find out,
he thinks very often that he is being required
to assume something in advance
in order to make the negation.
And therefore he balks at
that, and he won't do it.
K. No, because, sir, the brain needs security.
Otherwise it can't function. A. That's right.
K. So it finds security in a belief.
In an image, in rituals, in the
propaganda of two thousand or five thousand years.
And there is a sense
of safety, comfort, security, well-being,
somebody is looking after the
image of somebody greater than me
who is looking after me
inwardly, he is responsible, all that.
So when you are asking a
human being to negate all that,
he is faced with an immense sense of danger,
immense sense of... he becomes panicked.
A. Exactly. K. So, to see all that,
to see the absurdity of all the present religions,
the utter meaninglessness of it all,
and to face being totally insecure and not be frightened.
A. I sense a trick that
one can play on himself right here.
Again, I'm very grateful to you
that we're exploring together this pathology
in its various facets.
One can begin with the notion
that he's going to make this negation
in order to attain to something better.
K. No, that's not negation. A.
And that's not negation at all.
K. No. The negation is to deny what is false
not knowing what is, what is true.
To see the false in the false,
and to see the truth in the false.
And it is the truth that denies the false.
You don't deny the false,
but you see what is false.
And the very seeing of
what is false is the truth.
Right? A. Yes, of course.
K. And that denies, that sweeps away all this.
I don't know if I'm making myself clear.
A. Well, I had a
very interesting experience in class yesterday.
I had given the class an assignment.
I think I mentioned this
in a conversation we had yesterday.
I had given the class an assignment
to go and look at the tree.
So, in effect, I'm making a report
as to what happened after they came back.
Well, one young woman described what happened to her.
And she described it in such
a way that the class was convinced,
and I was convinced that there was no,
there was no blockage of her
looking between herself and this tree.
She was calmly ecstatic in her report.
That sounds like a curious juxtaposition of words,
but it seems to me to be correct.
But then I asked her a question,
and I said, well, now, were you
thinking of yourself as looking at this tree?
And she hesitated.
Mind you, she'd already gone through this whole statement,
which was very beautifully undertaken.
And I come along, playing the
role of the serpent in the garden,
you see, and I said, well, now,
might it not have been the case
that any time when you were doing this
that you thought of yourself looking at the tree?
K. That's the observer.
A. And with this hesitation,
she began to fall more and
more out of her own act.
Well, we had a look at that.
She and I and the class, we all
had a look at what she was doing.
Finally, she turned around and said,
well, the reason that I stopped
was not because of what went
on between me and the tree.
I'm very clear about that.
It's because I'm in class now,
it's because I'm in class now,
and I'm thinking that I
ought to say the right thing.
And so I've gone and ruined the whole thing.
It was a revelation not only to her,
but you could see with respect
to the faces all around the room
that we're all involved in this nonsense.
K. Yes, sir.
A. And her shock that she could so betray
this relationship that she'd had in doing her exercise,
in just a couple of words, was almost...
K. Very revealing.
A. Yes, extremely revealing, but at the same time
desperately hard to believe
that anybody would do such a thing to himself.
Please, please, go on.
K. Sir, sir, that's it.
Negation can only take place
when the mind sees the false.
The very perception of the false
is the negation of the false.
And when you see the religions,
based on miracles, based on personal worship,
based on the fear that you, yourself, your own life
is so shoddy, empty, meaningless, and it is so transient,
so distant, you're gone in a few years,
and the mind creates the image which is eternal,
which is marvellous, which is the beautiful, the heaven,
and identifies with it and worships it.
Because it needs a sense of security, deeply,
and it has created all this superficial nonsense,
a circus, it is a circus.
A. Oh, yes.
K. So, can the mind observe this phenomenon
and see its own demand
for security, comfort, safety, permanency,
and deny all that?
Deny in the sense, see how the brain, thought,
creates the sense of permanency,
eternity, or whatever you like to call it,
and to see all that.
Therefore, one has to go much more deeply, I think,
into the question of thought.
Because both in the West and the East,
thought has become the most important movement in life.
Right, sir? A. Oh, yes.
K. Thought, which has created
this marvellous world of technology,
marvellous world of science and all that,
and thought which has created the religions,
all the marvellous chants,
both the Gregorian and the Sanskrit chants,
thought which has built these beautiful cathedrals,
thought which has made images of the saviours,
the masters, the gurus, the father image,
and lest one, for example,
unless one really understands thought,
what is thinking,
we will still play the
same game in a different field.
A. Exactly.
K. Look what is happening in this country.
These gurus come from India.
They shave their head, put on the Indian dress,
a little tuft of hair hanging down,
and repeat endlessly what somebody has said.
A new guru. They have had old gurus, the priests,
the Catholic, and they have denied them,
but accept the others. You follow?
A. Yes.
K. The others are as dead as the old ones,
because they are just repeating tradition,
traditionally repeating how to sit, how to shave,
how to meditate, how to hold your head, breathe,
and finally obey what the old guru says,
or the young guru says,
which is exactly what took place in the Catholic world,
in the Protestant world. You follow?
They deny that, and yet accept the other,
because they want security.
They want somebody to tell them
what to do, what to think.
Never how to think.
A. No. This raises a question
that I hope we can explore together,
that concerns the word experience.
K. Oh yes, that's another one.
It's amazing how often, in these times,
this word crops up to represent something
that I desperately need, which somehow lies outside myself.
I need the experience of an awakening.
It isn't an awakening that I need, apparently,
it's an experience of this awakening.
The whole idea of religion as experience
seems to me to need very, very careful thought,
very, very careful penetration.
K. Quite true.
A. Very careful penetration.
K. Sir, if I may
ask, why do we demand experience?
Why do we demand ourselves?
Why is this craving for experience?
We have sexual experience,
experiences of every kind, don't we?
As we live.
Insults, flattery, happenings, incidents, influences,
people say, don't say, will you read
a book, and so on, so on.
We are experiencing all the time.
We are bored with that.
And we say, we go to somebody
who will give me the experience of God.
A. Yes, that's precisely what's claimed.
K. Yes. Now, what is involved in that?
What is involved in the demand for experience
and the experiencing of that demand?
I experience what that guru
or master or somebody tells me.
How do I know it is real?
And I recognise it, don't I, sir?
Look, I experience something.
And I can only know that I have experienced it
only when I have recognised it.
Right?
A. Right.
K. Recognition implies I've already known.
A. Recognise.
K. Recognise.
A. Yes.
K. So, I am experiencing what I have already known,
therefore it's nothing new.
A. Yes, you are making yourself very, very clear.
K. So, all they are doing is a self-deception.
A. It is actually lusted after.
K. Oh, good Lord!
A. Yes. The drive for it is extraordinary.
I've seen it in many, many students
who will go to extraordinary austerities.
Really.
K. Oh, I've noticed.
A. We sometimes think that young people today
are very loose in their behavior.
K. Yes.
A. But I have seen it.
We sometimes think that young people today
are very loose in their behavior.
Well, some are, but what's so new about that?
That's been going on since time out of mind.
I think that what is rarely seen
is that many, many young persons today
are extremely serious about acquiring something
that someone possesses that they don't have.
And if someone claims to have it,
naively, they are on their way.
And they'll go through any number of cartwheels,
they'll stand on their head indefinitely
for that that lies out.
K. I have seen all this.
A. Yes, which is called an experience as such.
K. That's why one has to be very careful,
as you pointed out, sir, to explore this word
and to see why the mind,
why a human being demands more experience.
When his whole life is a vast experience
with which he is so bored,
he thinks this is a new experience.
But to experience the new,
how can the mind recognise it as the new?
And this has already known it.
I don't know if I...
A. Yes, yes.
And there's something very remarkable here
in terms of what you said earlier.
In other previous conversations that we've had,
in the recognition of what is called the new,
the linkage with old thought, old image,
establishes the notion that there's something gradual
in the transition,
that there really is some kind of genuine link here
with where I am now and where I was before.
Now I become the next guru who goes out
and teaches the person how gradually
to undertake this discipline.
K. Yes, sir.
A. And it never stops.
No, no, no, I do see that.
It's amazing, it's amazing.
Driving down in the car this morning,
I was thinking about the whole business of chant.
That you mentioned, the beauty of it all.
And since this is related to experience as such,
I thought maybe we could examine the aesthetics
in terms of where this self-trapping lies in it.
And of course, I thought of Sanskrit
and that beautiful invocation that is chanted
to the Upanishad, the Isha.
Purnam adhar, purnam idam, purnat purnam udhacate,
purnasya purnam, and it goes on.
And I said to myself,
if one would attend to those words,
there's the echo of the abiding through the whole thing,
through that whole glorious cadence.
And yet within it, within it, there's
the radical occasion to fall into a euphoria.
K. Yes, sir.
A. And somnolence takes over.
But it's within the very same.
And I said to myself, well,
maybe Mr. Krishnamurti would say a word about the relation
of beauty to this in terms
of one's own relation to the beautiful,
when that relation is not seen for what it is.
Since there's an archosis present that I can generate,
it isn't in those words.
And yet we think that
the language must be at fault.
There must be something demonically hypnotic about this.
We do.
And then religious groups will
separate themselves totally from all this.
We had a period in
Europe when Protestants, Calvinists wouldn't allow
the use of the word, the word, to be used.
And we had a period in Europe
when we had a period in Europe
when Protestants, Calvinists wouldn't allow an organ to...
No music.
K. No music.
A. Because music is seductive.
I'm not the self-seducer, it's the music's fault.
K. Yes.
A. Let's look at that.
K. That is just it.
As we were saying the other day, sir, beauty
can only be when there is
the total abandonment of the self,
complete emptying the consciousness of
its content, which is the me.
Then there is a beauty which is something entirely different
from the pictures, charms, all that.
And probably most of these young
people, and also the older people,
seek beauty in that sense
through the trappings of the church,
through charms, through reading the
Old Testament with all its...
beautiful words and images and all that,
and that gives them a sense of deep satisfaction.
In other words, sir, what
they are seeking is really gratification
through beauty.
Beauty of word, beauty of things, beauty of the word,
beauty of the word, beauty of
the word, beauty of the word.
Beauty of word, beauty of
charm, beauty of all the robes
and the incense and the light of the...
coming through those marvellous pieces of colour.
You've seen it all in cathedrals,
North Qadam and Shaq and all these pieces.
More.
And it gives them a sense of sacredness,
a sense of feeling happy, relieved.
At last there is a place
where I can go and meditate,
be quiet, get into contact with something.
And when you come along
and say, look, that's all rubbish.
It has no meaning.
What has meaning is how
you live in your daily life.
Then they throw a brick at you.
A. Of course, it's like taking
food away from a starving dog.
K. Exactly.
Sir, this is the whole point, sir.
Experience is a trap.
And all the people who want this strange experience,
which the gurus think they have...
A. Which is always called the knowledge.
Interesting. K. Yes, very, very interesting.
A. Isn't it? It's always called the knowledge.
K. Knowledge.
A. Yes. Of course, I
was thinking of our previous conversations
about this self-transformation
that is not dependent on knowledge,
not dependent on time,
and eminently requires responsibility.
K. You see, and also,
sir, we don't want to work.
We work very strenuously in earning a livelihood.
Look what we do, year after year after year,
day after day, day after day,
the brutality, the ugliness of all that.
But here, inwardly, psychologically,
we don't want to work.
We are too lazy.
Let the other fellow work, perhaps he has worked,
and perhaps he'll give me something.
But I don't say, I'm going to find out.
I'll deny the whole thing and find out.
A. No, the assumption is that the priest's business
is to have worked in order to know
so that I am relieved of that task,
or if I didn't come
into the world with enough marbles,
then all I need do is simply follow his instructions,
and it's his fault if he gets it messed up.
K. Yes.
And we never ask the man who says,
I know, I have experienced, what do you know?
A. Exactly.
K. What have you experienced?
What do you know?
When you say, I know, you
only know something which is dead,
which is gone, which is finished, which is the past.
You can't know something that's living.
You follow, sir?
A. Yes.
K. A living thing you can never know, it's moving.
It is never the same.
And so I can never say, I know my wife.
Or my husband, my children,
because they are living human beings.
But these fellows come along, from India especially,
and they say, I know, I have experienced,
I have knowledge, I will give it to you.
And I say, what impudence!
You follow, sir?
What callous indifference that you know and I know,
and I know, and I know, and I know,
and you know, and I don't know.
And what do you know?
A. It's amazing what's been going on
in terms of the relation
between men on the one hand
and women on the other, or
man and woman with respect to this,
because a whole mythology has grown up about this.
For instance, woman, we say, our sex says,
woman is mysterious.
And never is this understood in
terms of the freshness of life,
which includes everything, not just woman.
Now we have an idea that woman is mysterious.
So we're talking about something in terms of an essence,
which has nothing to do with existence.
Isn't that what you're...
K. That's what you're saying.
A. Yes, yes. Goodness me!
And as you said earlier, we're actually taught this.
This is all in books,
this is all in the
conversations that go on in classrooms.
K. So that's why, sir, I feel,
education is destroying people, as it is now.
It has become a tragedy.
If I had a son,
which I haven't got, thank God,
I would say, where am I to educate him?
What am I to know with him?
To make him like the rest of the group,
like the rest of the community?
Thought, memories, accept, obey, you follow, sir?
All the things that are going on.
And when you are faced with
that, as many people are now,
they are faced with this problem.
A. Oh, they are, yes.
Yes, there's no question about that.
K. And so we say, look, let's start a school,
which we have in India,
which we're going to do in California, at Ojai.
We're going to do that.
Let's start a school where we think totally differently,
while we are taught differently.
Not just the original, but the original.
Not just the routine, routine, routine,
to accept or to deny,
react, you know, the whole thing.
So from that arises, sir, another question.
Why does the mind obey?
I obey the laws of the country.
I obey keeping to the left side of the road
or right side of the road.
I obey what the doctor tells me.
I'm careful what he tells me.
Personally, I don't go near doctors.
If I do, I'm very careful.
I listen very carefully to what they have to say.
I'm watchful.
I don't accept immediately this or that.
But politically, in a so-called democratic country,
in a so-called democratic world,
they won't accept a tyrant.
しばゆーCha insulted my words.
Freedom.
But spiritually, inwardly,
they accept every Tom, Dick and Harry.
Especially when they come from India.
A. Oh, yes.
K. The other day I turned on with London BBC
and there was a man
interviewing a certain group of people.
And the boy and the girl said,
we obey entirely what our guru says.
I said that.
And the interviewer said,
will he tell you to marry?
If he tells me, I will marry.
If he tells me I
must stop, I will stop, far.
Just a slave. You understand, sir?
And yet this very same person
would object to political tyranny.
A. Absurd. Yes.
K. There he will accept the
tyranny of a petty little guru
with his fanciful ideas,
and he will reject politically
a tyranny or a dictatorship.
So, why does the mind divide life
into accepting authority in one way, in one direction,
and deny it in another?
And what is the importance of authority?
That is, sir, the word authority, as you know,
means the one who originates.
A. Author. K. Author.
And these priests, gurus, leaders, spiritual preachers,
what have they originated?
They are repeating tradition, aren't they?
A. Oh yes, precisely.
K. And tradition, whether it is from the Zen tradition,
the Chinese tradition, or Hindu, is a dead thing.
And these people are perpetuating the dead thing.
The other day I saw a man,
he was explaining how to meditate,
put your hands here, close your eyes...
A. Yes, that's the one I saw.
K. ...and do this, that, and the other.
I said, good God! A. It was appalling.
K. And people accepted. You know, sir?
A. And on the same thing, there was this woman
who had run out of money, and every blessed thing,
she had nowhere to go to sleep, and so forth,
and hysterically she was saying,
I'm in line, I've got
all these people ahead of me,
but I must have this knowledge.
I must have this knowledge.
The hysteria of it, the desperation of it.
K. That's why, sir, what
is behind this acceptance of authority?
You understand?
The authority of law, the authority of the policeman,
the authority of the priest, the authority of these gurus,
what is behind this acceptance of authority?
Is it fear?
Fear of going wrong spiritually,
of not doing the right
thing in order to gain enlightenment,
knowledge, the super-consciousness, whatever it is,
is it fear?
Or is it a sense of despair,
a sense of utter loneliness, utter ignorance?
I'm using the word ignorance in
the deeper sense of the word.
A. Yes, yes, I follow.
K. Which makes me say, there
is a man there who says,
he knows, I'll accept him.
I don't reason. You follow, sir?
I don't say, what do you know?
What do you bring to us,
give to your own tradition from India?
Who cares?
You're bringing something dead, nothing original,
you follow, sir, nothing real,
but repeat, repeat, repeat, repeat what others have done.
我家
in India themselves are throwing out.
A. Yes, I was just thinking of Tennyson's lines
that, apropos of this, though in a different context,
when he wrote it,
there is not to reason
why, but to do and die.
K. Yes, the good old thing.
So what is behind this acceptance of authority?
A. It's interesting that the word authority
is radically related to the self,
or toss, the self.
There is this sensed, gaping void through the division.
K. Yes, sir, that's just...
A. Through the division.
And that immediately opens up a hunger, doesn't it?
And my projection of my meal I've run madly to.
K. You see, when you
see this, you want to cry.
You follow, sir?
A. Yes.
K. All these young people going to these gurus,
shaving their head, dressing in Indian dress,
dancing in the streets,
fantastic things they are doing,
all on a tradition which is dead.
All tradition is dead. You follow?
And when you see that, you say,
my God, what has happened?
So I go back and ask, why do we accept?
Why are we influenced by these people?
Why are we influenced when there is a constant repetition
in a commercial, buy this, buy this, buy this?
It's the same as that. You follow, sir?
Why do we accept?
The child accepts, I can understand that.
Poor thing, he doesn't know anything.
It needs security, it needs a mother,
it needs care, it needs protection,
it needs for it to
sit in your lap and become...
你跟着我
affectionate, kind, gentle, that it needs that.
Is it they think the guru gives them all this?
Through their words, through their rituals,
through their repetition, through their absurd disciplines,
you follow?
Sense of acceptance,
as I accept my mother and child,
I accept that in order to be comfortable,
in order to feel at last something after me.
This relates to what you said in a previous conversation
when we looked into fear.
The reaction of the infant
is a reaction with no intermediary
of any kind of his own contrivance.
He simply recognises that he has a need.
And this is not an imagined
want, it is a radical need.
He needs to feed,
he needs to be affectionately held.
The transition from that to the point where one,
as he gets older, begins to think
about the source of the meeting of that need.
It emerges as the image that is interposed
between the sense of danger and the immediate action.
So, if I'm understanding you correctly,
there's a deflection here from the radical purity of act.
K. That's right, sir.
A. And I've done that myself.
I have done that myself.
It isn't because of anything that I was told
that actually coerced me to do it,
even though what you say is true.
We are continually invited.
It's a kind of siren-like call that comes to us
throughout the entire culture, in all cultures,
to start that stuff.
K. Sir, that's what I want to get at.
Why is it that we accept authority?
In the democratic world,
politically you would shun any dictator.
But yet, religiously, they are all dictators.
And why do we accept it?
Why do I accept the
priest as an intermediary to something
which he says he knows?
And so it shows, sir, we stop reasoning.
Politically we reason,
we see how important it is to be free,
free speech, free everything, free, as much as possible.
We never think freedom is necessary here.
Spiritually we don't feel the necessity of freedom,
and therefore we accept it.
Any time, dick and hair, it is horrifying.
The most, I've seen intellectuals, professors, scientists
falling for all this trap.
Because they have reasoned in the scientific world
and are weary of reasoning,
and here at last I can sit back, not reason,
be told, be comfortable, be happy,
I'll do all the work for you,
you don't have to do anything,
I'll take you over the river. You follow?
A. Oh, yes.
K. And I'm delighted.
So, we accept where there is ignorance,
where reason doesn't function,
where intelligence is an abeyance,
and you need all that
– freedom, intelligence, reasoning,
in with regard to real spiritual matters.
我都會說
Some guru comes along and tells you what to do,
and you repeat what he does.
You follow, sir, how destructive it is?
How degenerate it is, that's what's happening.
I don't think these gurus realise what they are doing.
They are encouraging degeneracy.
A. Well, they represent...
A chain of the same.
K. Exactly.
So can we...
Sir, this brings up a very important question.
Can there be an education
in which there is no authority whatsoever?
A. I must say yes to that,
in terms of the experience
that I had in class yesterday.
It was a tremendous shock to the students
when they suspended their disbelief for a moment,
just to see whether I meant it when I said,
now, we must do this together.
Not you are doing what I say to do.
K. Do it to work together.
A. We will do this together.
K. Share it together.
A. Right. You will question and I will question
and we'll try to grasp
as we go along without trying.
And I went into the business about
let's not have this shoddy little thing trying.
K. Quite right.
A. That took a little while.
That increased the shock
because the students who have been,
to their own great satisfaction,
what you would call, devoted,
those who do their work, who make effort,
are suddenly finding out that this
man has come into the room
and he's giving trying a bad press.
This does seem to turn the thing completely upside down.
But they showed courage in the sense that
they gave it a little attention
before beginning the true act of attention.
That's why I was using courage there,
because it's a preliminary to that.
I've quite followed you when you have raised the question
about the relation of courage
to the pure act of attention.
It seems to me that that's not where it belongs.
K. No.
A. But they did get
it up for this preliminary step.
But then we ran into this,
what I think I called in an earlier conversation,
dropping a stitch, where they really saw this abyss.
They were alert enough to stand over
the precipice, and that caused them to freeze.
It's that moment that seems to me absolutely decisive.
It's almost like one sees in terms of events
objective events.
I remember reading the Spanish philosopher Ortega,
who spoke of events that
tremble back and forth before
the thing actually tumbles into itself.
Well, that was happening in the room.
But it was like water that moved
up to the lip of the cup
and couldn't quite spill.
A. No, over.
K. Correct.
A. I've spoken about this at some length,
because I wanted to describe to you a real situation,
what was actually happening.
K. I was going to say, sir,
I've connected with very many
schools for forty years and more,
and when one talks to the students
about freedom and authority and acceptance,
they're completely lost.
A. Yes.
K. They want to be slaves.
My father says this, I must do this,
or my father says, I won't do that.
It's the same.
A. Exactly.
Do you think in our next conversation we could...
انظر
at that moment of hesitation.
It seems to me so terribly critical for education itself.
Wonderful.